Let's talk about the new oral
testosterone that seems promising now
because I'm curious. Up till now, I've
always heard that oral testosterone does
not work.
Yeah. So, Stephen, I'm excited to see
that there is a new development in the
world of testosterone replacement. It's
the oral testosterone and specifically
testosterone underoid. So testosterone
underoid is an estester that's been used
for long term and the injectable um the
injectable for it is nebido. It's the
inject the the testosterone you inject
every um two to three months and that
lasts a long time in your in your
system. Well over the past five I think
even eight to 10 years they've developed
the oral testosterone under canoid and
I've been keeping a very close eye on
it. There were different brand names
that have come out that I've used in my
patients that I had so so success.
First, there was a a Troy form that was
pure testosterone and up USB that we've
used again. We've had so results. My
patients maybe 25% of my patients would
say, "Okay, yes, I feel good enough.
I'll stay on it." Not maybe not even
that much. Testosterone canoid. I used
one brand name before called Jatenzo
that I like but I did not get great
results for it. The latest oral
testosterone that I've been using and
that I've been really looking at is
called Kaisotrix. And Kaisotrix again I
feel like they've really improved on the
testosterone on the canoid and I'm
getting really good results with my
patients. We've switched more than a
hundred patients now on oral Kaiser and
we're getting great results. And the key
to all the the testosterone on the
canoid oral is that it's not absorbed
through the lift. It doesn't go to the B
first bypass of the liver. It's absorbed
to the intestinal lymphatics. So it
bypasses the liver. So that issue that
everybody knows that oral testosterone
can cause liver toxicity. Not with this
form. The one thing that's kind of a
pain with oral testosterone, you have to
eat kind of some fat with it to be
absorbed. So a lot of our patients in
our wellness clinic are fasting and
we've always promoted fasting. So my
patients who take oil testosterone and
again what I like with Kais versus
Jatenzo that you don't need to have a
highfat meal to be able to absorb it a
small amount of meal. So most of our
patients what we have them do we have
them take a tablespoon of good quality
olive oil that is a good thing anyway
for the polyphenols and then you take
that with your oral testosterone and
with this it shows really good
absorption so it's usually dosed twice a
day what we like with it is that it goes
in and out very quickly the halflife is
about four to six hours so you need to
take it twice twice a day but let me
tell you what the benefits are because
it is such a short halflife it does not
cause the negative feedback loop to the
pituitary. So you don't stop your own
production. So the side effects of
testosterone that we're always worried
about is decreased fertility, testicular
atrophy or decrease of your own
production. We don't have that with the
oral testosterone. Also another big
thing you know with injectable
testosterone we have maybe 30% of our
patients who develop secondary
ariththroytosis a high hemoglobin and
hematocrine. And for my patients who
have underlying sleep apnnea, you see
that even more. So there's always a lot
of discussion in the testosterone
forums. What should we do about a high
hemoglobin, right? If it's maybe 50 52,
you may not feel it too much, but we
know that if it's about 54, if it's 56,
58, a lot of patients are symptomatic
and there's still a possibility of
increased risk of heart disease, clots
or or stroke. And no matter what the
studies are, it's not conclusive, but in
the US, there is a standard of care from
the American Association of
Endocrinology that says that if your
immacul at risk of developing um
cardiovascular disease or clots and I
have a patient, a colleague, another
patient, a colleague of mine who got in
trouble recently and is being sued
because a patient who was on
testosterone had a mitoid of about 56
and had a stroke. They cannot prove that
the stroke was due because of this, but
because he didn't follow standard of
care, he's being sued. So what I do with
my patients when they have a hematocrit
above 54, a lot of them are symptomatic
anyway. I don't want to keep him that
way. I'll change the dose. I'll put them
maybe to daily injections. Make sure
that they stay hydrated. There are
supplements like nanocynise that can
help with this. We do blood donation
while you monitor the feritin. You know,
we've talked about this a lot. So
there's a lot of management that you
need to do when a patient develops that.
You don't get that with the oral
testosterone. So for my patients who
have issues with thick blood, oral
kaisot is a really good option. For my
younger patients who still desire
fertility, you maintain fertility while
on testosterone. So again, we've said
that, right? Um before we always thought
that testosterone was just u lot only
happen in old men. Um delayed onset
hypogonadism happened in your 50s and
60s. That's not the reality anymore. The
average patient in my clinic is 37 with
real low tea, real testosterone
deficiency. So if I have a young patient
now who comes to me still desires
fertility, the option we always had is
to combine testosterone plus hCG or
testosterone with enlophine which I
don't love. I like hcg much more but now
we have another option oral testosterone
under canoid and now what I'm seeing
with my patient with oral kaisotra
almost we got almost a
75% positive response on our patients.
The patients that I see are not maybe
loving it as much is patients who were
used to injections. So they are used to
those high levels for them they like
this. But especially if a patient is new
to testosterone they love the Kaisotrix
and for the patients who have issue that
becomes a really good option. So I'm
excited about this. I can't wait to see
that more people are going to use it.
But if you go on a lot of I I go on
Reddit and those thread of forums a lot
to try to see what are people saying
about it. mostly positive about that old
Kaiser tren. So really interesting and
we'll just have to keep an eye on it. Is
it expensive? It is more expensive than
the injection. Um but it's still that I
don't remember the numbers and we won't
go over numbers there, but it is more
expensive than the injection. But if you
com if you compare testosterone plus hcg
versus kaotrix by itself, now it becomes
more cost effective. And if you compare
that you have and I had a patient the
other day with this. He has underlying
sleep apnnea. No matter what we do, his
hematocrit was in the 58 range. He's
symptomatic with it. Um and you know
like when when they when they tried
doing even his his um blood donation,
the the flabbotomy sent me a picture.
His blood was so thick it could barely
come out of the needle. I can't leave a
patient with such thick blood. I don't
care what people are going to say that
there's no study that there's harm. The
patient freaked out and I freaked out.
The blood was solid. I'm like, "No, we
can't keep you." I switched them to
micro doing daily injections, lots of
water, nattokynise. I put them on a baby
aspirin. Still stayed high. I switched
him to a
kaisot. Within four weeks, his
hemoglobin went down. He felt great. He
didn't have the Sometimes when you have
high hemoglobin, you have a sensation of
heat in your head. You feel your blood
pressure can go up. All of this went
away. So, this guy's so happy and he's
like, "Now I don't even have to inject
myself anymore." That's the other
benefit of Kaisotrix. A lot of
resistance of patients to go on TLT is
they don't want to inject themselves. So
now that can go and and help those
patients
[Music]